{"tossups": [{"question": "Scipione Li Volsi [[skip-ee-OH-neh lee VOHL-see]] made this man a statue in Palermo commemorating his conquest of Tunis. Upon his retirement, this man lived in the Monastery of Yuste [[YOO-steh]]. During this man's rule, Maurice of Saxony and Henry II of France fought his government in the Second Schmalkaldic [[shmahl-KAHL-dik]] War, leading to the Peace of Passau and Peace of Augsburg. This man's army sacked Rome in 1527, and this emperor ordered Martin Luther to appear at the Diet [[DEE-eht]] of Worms [[VURMS]]. For the point, name this king of Spain and Holy Roman Emperor.", "answer": "<b><u>Charles V</u></b> (accept <b><u>Carlos I</u></b> or <b><u>Charles I</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A ruler of this empire killed Mihrak Andigan [[MEE-rahk AHN-dih-gahn]] and created the RGDS trilingual inscription. Papak's son founded this empire, which was described in the <em>Letter of Tansar</em>. Chiefs of this empire were called <em>Spahbods</em>, and Ahura Mazda was shown next to this empire's founder, Ardashir I, in a carving at Naqsh-e Rustam [[NAHKSH-eh ROOS-tahm]]. This empire chose the name \"Iran'' for the land it ruled. For the point, name this Neo-Persian successor of the Parthian Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Sassanid</u></b> [[SAH-sah-nid]] Empire (accept <b><u>Sassanid</u></b>s; accept Empire of the <b><u>Iranian</u></b>s before mentioned; accept <b><u>Neo-Persian</u></b> Empire before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This composer wrote a posthumously-published string quintet based on \u201cDie Forelle\u201d [[dee for-ELL-uh]], this man's popular song about a fish. This man's \u201cGreat\u201d C-Major symphony was also published after his death. This Austrian wrote over six hundred songs, or <em>lieder</em> [[LEE-duh]], including two lengthy song cycles based on poems by Wilhelm M\u00fcller [[MYOO-luh]]. At the age of eighteen, this man set Goethe\u2019s [[GEHR-tuhs]] \u201cErlk\u00f6nig\u201d [[EHRL-kuh-nig]] to music. For the point, what composer wrote the <em>Trout Quintet</em> and two movements of the <em>Unfinished Symphony</em>?", "answer": "Franz <b><u>Schubert</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "During this conflict, Yang Xiuqing [[YAHNG SHOO-CHING]] was killed in the Tianjing Incident. The Xiang [[SHE-AHNG]] army with <em>tuanlian</em> [[TWAHN-LYAHN]] forces was used by Zeng Guofan [[ZUNG GWOH-FAHN]] to fight rebels in this war. To end this war, the Ever Victorious Army of \"Chinese\" Gordon was founded. Many Hakka joined this rebellion, which was led by the self-proclaimed Brother of Jesus, Hong Xiuquan [[SHOO-KWAHN]]. For the point, name this rebellion which created a Heavenly Kingdom to fight the Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty.", "answer": "<b><u>Taiping</u></b> Rebellion (accept <b><u>Taiping</u></b> Civil War; accept <b><u>Taiping</u></b> Revolution)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man likely ordered the bombing of Avianca Flight 203 in an attempt to influence his country's 1990 elections. The first \"Search Bloc,\" under the command of Hugo Martinez, was created by Virgilio [[veer-HEE-lee-oh]] Barco with the sole goal of apprehending this man. After this man's death, four hippos that he kept at Hacienda N\u00e1poles escaped confinement and have since become an invasive species in this man's country. The Medell\u00edn [[meh-deh-YEEN]] Cartel was led by, for the point, what notorious Colombian drug lord?", "answer": "Pablo <b><u>Escobar</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 2000, a non-Israeli Six Day War took place in this country which hosts community militias called Mai-Mai. Lendu-speakers in this country organized under an association named CODECO in the Ituri [[ee-TOO-ree]] War. In this country, the M23 movement seized Goma, and many Pygmies have been genocidally killed in this country's North Kivu province. One political party in this country is named Rally for Democracy, and this country's ADFLC was led by Laurent-Desire Kabila [[loh-RAHNT deh-sih-REH kah-BEE-lah]]. Once known as Zaire, for the point, what is this Central African nation?", "answer": "<b><u>Democratic Republic of the Congo</u></b> (accept <b><u>DRC</u></b>; accept <b><u>Congo-Kinshasa</u></b>; accept <b><u>DR Congo</u></b>; accept <b><u>DROC</u></b>; prompt on the \"Congo\"; do not accept or prompt on \"Republic of the Congo\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This hero\u2019s second wife fell in love with his son by an Amazonian queen. This adventurer accompanied his friend Pirithous [[PEER-uh-thus]] to the underworld, where he was trapped by Hades until Heracles rescued him. As a young man, this hero slew several bandits, including Sciron [[SKY-ron]], Sinis, and Procrustes [[proh-KRUS-teez]]. On the island of Crete, Ariadne gave this man a ball of string to help him find his way out of Daedalus\u2019s labyrinth. For the point, what mythological founder of Athens slew the Minotaur?", "answer": "<b><u>Theseus</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This leader was criticized for rejecting Zimey Rinpoche's [[zee-MAY rin-poh-CHAYS]] <em>Yellow Book</em>, which he claimed only served to support \"sectarian divisiveness.\" A delegation sent to Beijing by this leader in 1951 allegedly agreed to the Seventeen Point Agreement without this man's authorization. In 1959, an uprising against China forced this leader to flee the Potala Palace and begin his exile in India. For the point, name this leader of Tibetan Buddhism.", "answer": "14th <b><u>Dalai Lama</u></b> (accept Tenzin <b><u>Gyatso</u></b>; accept Lhamo <b><u>Dhondup</u></b>; accept Gyalwa <b><u>Rinpoche</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city was ruled by one of the Seven Sages, Periander, who was also one of the Two Tyrants along with Cypselus [[SIP-seh-luss]]. This city's ports included Lechaion [[leh-KAY-on]] and Kencheai [[KEN-kay-aye]], and this city's <em>hoplites</em> wore helmets which covered the head and neck. Lucius Mummius sacked this city for Rome, and the Peloponnesian War broke out when this city's colony of K\u00e9rkyra [[KEHR-kee-rah]] allied with Athens. For the point, name this southern Greek city on a namesake isthmus.", "answer": "<b><u>Corinth</u></b> (Accept <b><u>K\u00f3rinth</u></b>os)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man took 36 hours over six days to give the <em>Nutuk</em> speech, explaining events in his country from 1919 to 1923. This man's reforms included requiring surnames, such as those ending in \"oglu.\" In 1951, Adnan Menderes [[MAN-deh-rehs]] passed a law banning any insults of this man. This man developed the Sun Language Theory which stated that all languages came from Central Asia. This man devised the Six Arrows to distinguish his people from the Ottomans. Establishing a national capital at Ankara, for the point, who was this \"Father of the Turks\"?", "answer": "Mustafa Kemal <b><u>Atat\u00fcrk</u></b> (accept Mustafa Kemal <b><u>Pasha</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s Rule of Signs provided a method for finding the positive real roots of a polynomial. This \"father of analytical geometry\" changed how mathematicians viewed algebra in his work <em>La G\u00e9om\u00e9trie</em>. In <em>Meditations on First Philosophy</em>, this skeptic arrived at only one statement he believed that he could know for certain, \"<em>Cogito ergo sum</em>\" [[KAH-gee-toh EHR-goh SOOM]]. For the point, name this Frenchman who invented the <em>x-y</em> coordinate system and concluded, \u201cI think. Therefore, I am.\u201d", "answer": "Ren\u00e9 <b><u>Descartes</u></b> [[day-KAHRT]]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "During this war, Operation Mistral 2 coincided with Operation Deliberate Force, a NATO air campaign commanded by U.S. Admiral Leighton Smith. A U.N.-designated \u201csafe area\u201d came under siege by VRS forces led by Ratko Mladi\u0107 [[MLAH-ditch]] during this war. The first genocide in Europe since World War Two occurred during this war, which ended with the 1995 Dayton Accords. For the point, name this war between proto-states sponsored by Croatia and Serbia, a part of the larger Yugoslav Wars.", "answer": "<b><u>Bosnia</u></b>n War (prompt on \"Yugoslav War(s)\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Oswaldo Lopez Arellano [[ah-reh-YAH-noh]] instituted military rule in this country where Tiburcio [[tee-BOOR-see-oh]] Car\u00edas Andino ruled. During the Hundred Hours' War, this country attacked a smaller neighbor after rioting during a qualifying event for the 1970 FIFA [[FEE-fah]] World Cup. In 2009, this country's president, Jose Manuel Zelaya Rosales, was removed from power. O. Henry coined the term \"banana republic\" to describe, for the point, which country with capital at Tegucigalpa [[teh-GOO-see-GAHL-pah]]?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Honduras</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This country was the site of the \"God Save the Queen\" Plot and the GMA-7 Incident. Fidel Ramos succeeded a president of this country who was involved in the Mendiola Massacre. This country was the location of the People Power Revolution during which Benigno Aquino [[beh-NEE-noh ah-KEE-noh]] was assassinated. Aquino's wife, Corazon, succeeded Ferdinand Marcos as president of this country. The site of the 1991 eruption of Mount Pinatubo, for the point, what is this Asian island nation, a former U.S. colony?", "answer": "Republic of the <b><u>Philippines</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "On a voyage to explore this landmass, one man said, \"I am just going outside and may be some time.\" That man, Captain Lawrence Oates, was one of the members of the failed <em>Terra Nova</em> mission to explore this landmass. Edward J. Bird, who visited this landmass in the 1840s, is the namesake a shield volcano on this landmass. Robert Scott and Ernest Shackleton led unsuccessful expeditions on this fifth-largest continent, the driest on Earth. Ross Island and Mt. Erebus [[EHR-eh-bus]] are located on, for the point, what southernmost continent?", "answer": "<b><u>Antarctica</u></b> (do not accept or prompt on \u201cSouth Pole\u201d)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This group, of which John Smoke Johnson was a leader, believed in the Tree of Peace. This group signed the Treaty of Canandaigua [[kah-nahn-DAI-gwah]] with George Washington. Wampum belts were used by this group, whose leader, Jigonhsasee [[jih-GOHN-sah-say]], served as a co-founder alongside the Great Peacemaker. The sachem [[SAH-kehm]] Tadodaho was convinced to join this group, bringing the Onondaga in as members. One of this group's founders was Hiawatha, a leader of the Mohawk. For the point, name this Native American Confederacy.", "answer": "<b><u>Iroquois</u></b> Confederacy (accept <b><u>Haudenosaunee</u></b>; accept <b><u>Iroquois</u></b> League; accept <b><u>Five Nations</u></b>; accept <b><u>Six Nations</u></b>; accept <b><u>Mohawk</u></b> before Jigonhsasee)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country was the site of Operation Jumelles [[joo-MEHL], during which the SDECE carried out Operation Blue Bird against the Kabyle [[kah-BEEL]] people. <em>Fellaghas</em> attacked <em>Pied-Noirs</em> [[peed-NWAHR]] civilians in this country's city of Philippeville. Charles De Gaulle returned to power after a crisis in this country led to Jacques Massu's coup attempt. The Evian Accords granted independence, for the point, in what former colony of France in North Africa?", "answer": "People's Democratic Republic of <b><u>Algeria</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This character is depicted in a book they also narrate whose central premise may have been inspired by the murder of Emmitt Till. This character sits with Black characters in an upper balcony during a trial, and with her brother, this character befriends Dill, who was inspired by the author\u2019s real-life friend, Truman Capote. This female character\u2019s hometown of Maycomb [[MAY-kum]] was inspired by Monroeville, Alabama, the birthplace of this novel's author. For the point, name this character from Harper Lee\u2018s novels <em>Go Set a</em> <em>Watchman</em> and <em>To Kill a Mockingbird</em>.", "answer": "Jean Louise \"<b><u>S</u></b>cout\" <b><u>Finch</u></b> (accept <b><u>Scout</u></b>; accept <b><u>Jean</u></b> Louise <b><u>Finch</u></b>; accept <b><u>Jean</u> </b>Louise)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "In this country, a city founded in the 18th century by Thao Kham Phong [[TAO-KAHM-PHUNG]] has a name which translates to \u201cRoyal Lotus City,\u201d Ubon Ratchathani [[OO-bahn rah-tchah-THAH-nee]]. In 1900, Russian explorer Pyotr Kuzmich Kozlov discovered the source of the river that forms much of this country's eastern border, the Mekong. The man who became king of this country in 2016 from the Chakri Dynasty took the name Rama X [[TENTH]] upon officially taking power. For the point, name this country, once known as Siam.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Thailand</u></b> (accept <b><u>Siam</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An appearance of this thing led to the construction of a Baroque column on the Graben and inspired the legend of \"Lieber Augustin,\" a street musician who stayed healthy due to his drunkenness. An event caused by this thing was related by both Daniel Defoe and Samuel Pepys [[PEEPS]]. Prevalent symptoms caused by this thing may have inspired the rhyme \"Ring a Ring o' Roses.\" London was struck by this disease in 1666 during the Second Pandemic. For the point, name this disease which led to the Black Death.", "answer": "<b><u>Bubonic Plague</u></b> (prompt on \"Plague\" or \"Black Plague\"; prompt on \"Great Plague of London\"; prompt on \"Black Death\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This island's Revolutionary Committee secured the right to create a gendarmerie [[zhahn-DAHR-muh-ree]], as well as other general autonomy, as part of the Pact of Halepa [[hah-LEH-pah]]. A certain country's Prince George resigned as high commissioner of this island in the aftermath of the Theriso revolt. This island was seized by the Ottoman Empire in 1669 following the Siege of Candia. For the point, name this island which was led from Heraklion [[heh-RAK-lee-un]] until reuniting with Greece in 1913.", "answer": "<b><u>Crete</u></b> (accept <b><u>Kr\u00edti</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Radio jamming was first used in this war at a battle which featured fighting at the Orphan Hills and 203 Meter Hill. Honghuzi [[HOHNG-HOO-ZEE]] were recruited as <em>chunchu</em> [[CHOON-choo]] sabotage units during this war. This war also featured land battles at Mukden and Port Arthur. This war featured a battle in which battleships under Admiral Togo sunk the fleet of Zinovy Rozhestvensky [[roh-zhest-VEN-skee]] at Tsushima [[tsoo-SHE-mah]] Strait. For the point, name this war which was ended by the 1905 Treaty of Portsmouth.", "answer": "<b><u>Russo-Japanese</u></b> War (accept <b><u>Japanese-Russian</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This Leiden native was popular for his ingeniously arranged group portraits, such as his painting of the <em>Syndics of the Drapers Guild</em> and his huge canvas of the Militia Company of District Two under the Command of Captain Frans Banning Cocq. One of this painter\u2019s works depicts Aristotle, in Baroque dress, contemplating a bust of the Greek poet Homer. For the point, what Dutch artist painted <em>The Anatomy Lesson of Dr. Nicholaes Tulp</em> and <em>The</em> <em>Night Watch</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Rembrandt</u></b> van Rijn", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This medical school dropout enrolled in divinity school at Cambridge where he mapped strata in Wales with Adam Sedgwick and developed his ideas on the \"divine design\" in nature. After gathering thousands of specimens and fossils on a five-year journey, this man returned to England aboard the HMS <em>Beagle</em>. Twenty years later, in 1859, this author published <em>On the Origin of Species</em>. The theory of evolution through natural selection was first articulated by, for the point, what Victorian naturalist?", "answer": "Charles <b><u>Darwin</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "This television series was the first British comedy to win a Golden Globe when it was named the Best Television series: Musical or Comedy in 2003. Ricky Gervais [[jehr-VAIS]] also won the Golden Globe that year for his portrayal of David Brent on this series. The theme song for this series, \"Handbags and Gladrags\" by Mike d'Abo, was replaced by an instrumental piece written by James Ferguson for the American version of this show. For the point, what BBC series was reimagined for NBC, creating a hit show set in Scranton, Pennsylvania?", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Office</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In 1967, Jean Drapeau [[ZHAHN drah-POH]] signed a secret agreement to transport this structure to Canada. The Brazilian aviator Alberto Santos-Dumont won a prize for a successful flight around this structure in 1901. A decision by \u00c9douard Lockroy nearly guaranteed this structure's completion which was opposed by the \"Committee of the 300.\" A member of that committee, Guy de Maupassant, was said to have regularly eaten at this structure's restaurant so that he wouldn't have to see it. Built for the 1889 World's Fair, for the point, what is this \"tower\" in Paris?", "answer": "<b><u>Eiffel</u></b> Tower (or Tour d'<b><u>Eiffel</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Jacob Wagner and Daniel Brent attempted to refuse to testify during this event. William Cushing and Alfred Moore recused themselves from this case which determined that the court could not decree a writ of <em>mandamus</em> [[man-DAY-muss]]. The plaintiff in this Supreme Court case was appointed Justice of the Peace but never received his commission, all in an attempt to thwart John Adams\u2019s \u201cmidnight judges.\u201d For the point, name this case from the Marshall court which established judicial review.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Marbury v. Madison</u></b></em> (or <em>William</em> <em><b><u>Marbury v.</u></b> James</em> <em><b><u>Madison</u></b>, Secretary of State of</em> <em>the United States</em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Nicolino de Pasquale [[pah-SKWAH-leh]] claimed these people used base 40 representations. This empire had feminine schools called <em>Aklla wasi</em>, and these people used abacus-type devices called <em>yupana</em>. Felipe Poma de Ayala created a book about the recording devices made of camelid fibers which these people used to record information like <em>mita</em>, their mandatory public service. This empire had Chasqui runners who ate coca leaves and used <em>quipu</em> [[KEE-poo]] knotted strings to keep records. For the point, name this Quechua [[KEH-chwah]]-speaking South American empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Inca</u></b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Anthony Meyer attempted to wrest party leadership from this person who was attacked by the deputy prime minister, Geoffrey Howe, during his resignation over the Exchange Rate Mechanism Plan. Douglas Hurd and Michael Heseltine were unsuccessful in their attempts to succeed this person who was ultimately succeeded by John Major. This person resigned from the Conservative Party over issues like the Community Charge poll tax . For the point, name this \"Iron Lady,\" the first female prime minister of the U.K.", "answer": "Margaret <b><u>Thatcher</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person forced TC Energy to lay off one thousand employees after cancelling a major project. A Georgia representative filed six articles of impeachment against this person for abuse of power. This man proposed the American Rescue Plan, which included $1,400 direct payments to Americans, and nominated cabinet officials including Marcia Fudge, Deb Haaland [[HAH-lund]], and Lloyd Austin. For the point, name this U.S. senator from Delaware and 46th U.S. president.", "answer": "Joseph \"Joe\" <b><u>Biden</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This politician was given hundreds of flour sacks as gifts while chairman of the Commission for Relief in Belgium during World War One. This politician was later appointed to lead the U.S. Food Administration and ordered Douglas MacArthur to confront the Bonus Army, hindering his chances of reelection. This Secretary of Commerce during the Prohibition era implemented the Smoot\u2013Hawley Tariff, which did little to improve the economy after Black Tuesday. For the point, name this president during the start of the Great Depression.", "answer": "Herbert Clark <b><u>Hoover</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}